<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen, upon Ephes. 5.16. Redeeming the time, because the days are evil. By the Reverend Father Philip Ellis monk of the H. Order of St. Benedict, and of the English Congr. chaplain and preacher in ordinary to their Majesties. Published by His Majesties command</title>
            <author>Ellis, Philip, 1652-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826717</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826717</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39288)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1829:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King and Queen, upon Ephes. 5.16. Redeeming the time, because the days are evil. By the Reverend Father Philip Ellis monk of the H. Order of St. Benedict, and of the English Congr. chaplain and preacher in ordinary to their Majesties. Published by His Majesties command</title>
                  <author>Ellis, Philip, 1652-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, printer to the King's most excellent Majesty, for his houshold and chapel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Trinity College Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Ephesians V,16 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31122:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the King and Queen, Upon Epheſ. 5.16. <hi>Redeeming the Time, becauſe the days are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Reverend Father <hi>Philip Ellis</hi> Monk of the H. Order of St. <hi>Benedict,</hi> and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Congr. Chaplain and Preacher in Ordinary to their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, for His Houſhold and Chapel, 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:31122:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:31122:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 5.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Redimentes tempus, quoniam dies mali ſunt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>Redeeming the Time, becauſe the days are evil.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F this great Apoſtle (Sacred Majeſty,) command all who were to ſucceed him in the Apoſtolical Office, and in the care of Souls, <hi>to Preach the Word in ſeaſon &amp; out of ſeaſon;</hi> certainly, this which I have choſen, or rather which is recommended this day by the Church to your particular conſideration, and is delivered by Him as a Compendium of Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, is ever <hi>in Seaſon,</hi> and ever in the <hi>Criſis:</hi> The management of our <hi>Time,</hi> being like the Dict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates of our Conſcience, in no circumſtance to be neglected, being in the number of thoſe Precepts which admit of no diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Time</hi> being in a continual <hi>Flux</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> every particle of it which is not <hi>improv'd</hi> is <hi>loſt;</hi> but, bleſſed be God, not loſt beyond <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> for what is impoſſible to Nature is poſſible to Grace; what all the induſtry of Man
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31122:3"/>cannot retrieve, nor the Wealth of both the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> recover, the pooreſt and weakeſt Chriſtian is taught how to Redeem: <hi>Redeem the Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should a Merchant ſee that Veſſel ſink be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Eyes which was laden with all his Hopes, and almoſt all his Wealth, where he had trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd up the labors of his <hi>paſt</hi> life, the comforts of his <hi>preſent,</hi> and the unknown joys of his <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> happineſs; yet admiſt his Agonies ſhould hear one promiſing to repair his loſs with the ſmall remainder of his Fortune; how greedily would he embrace the offer, and hearken to the expedient? Should an Eminent Lawyer whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per a young Spend-thrift in the ear, that he will put him into a method how to redeem a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd and imbeſled Eſtate, and this without any coſt or charges, and even any advantage to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Would not he look upon this Man as his better Genius, not only as the moſt charitable, but alſo the moſt friendly Perſon in the World, and follow his counſel in deſpite of all their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings and diſſuaſives, who encourage his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs, and lend a helping hand to his ruin? Should the <hi>Captive</hi> be taught how to recover his <hi>Liberty,</hi> the <hi>Conquered</hi> his <hi>Honor,</hi> the <hi>Stigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd</hi> and <hi>Scandalous</hi> his <hi>Reputation,</hi> or the <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor</hi> how to gain his <hi>Judge,</hi> and compound for the <hi>greateſt Crimes</hi> with the <hi>ſmalleſt Puniſhment;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:31122:3"/>I preſume much Rhetoric would not be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to win their attention. Now this is what I come to offer you, and what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> exhorts you to: But methinks, Exhortation ſhould be needleſs where Self-intereſt pleads ſo ſtrong; and I ſhould have nothing to do, but to ſhew you the <hi>practical Part,</hi> were all Men agreed in the <hi>Theſis.</hi> But moſt People know not the true price of <hi>Time,</hi> know not how to ſpend it when they have it, or how to go about to redeem it when it is miſ-ſpent.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, <hi>the true value of Time; the great abuſe of it, and the moſt excellent manner of redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it;</hi> I beg leave, may be the Subject of the two following Parts of my Diſcourſe, after we have implor'd the Divine Aſſiſtance, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Virgin Mother, <hi>Ave Maria.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>Redeem the Time, becauſe the days are evil.</head>
               <p>St. <hi>Aug.</hi> in his 24th Sermon upon the words of the Apoſtle, obſerves there are two things which render <hi>our days evil,</hi> the <hi>miſery</hi> and the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of Men. But ſince miſery is only the puniſhment of wickedneſs, and wickedneſs the cauſe of miſery, it is the miſ-ſpending and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming our Time, which denominate the days evil: Miſ-ſpending, relates to the preſent, and to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31122:4"/>the future when it becomes preſent; not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming, regards what is paſt; ſo that both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether infect the whole Stream, and render our days guilty of a double iniquity. For it is no ſmall aggravation of every ſin, (tho ſo little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on, and made ſo light of by People now a-days,) that in the <hi>perpetration</hi> of evil is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>omiſſion</hi> of doing well; that the ſame par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of Time we dedicate to <hi>Vice,</hi> ought to be conſecrated to the exerciſe of <hi>Vertue;</hi> that the contrary practice, beſides its proper and ſpecifick wickedneſs, is guilty of Injuſtice and Robbery. In fine, That in the day of Judgment a ſeparate account will be demanded of what we <hi>have,</hi> and what we <hi>have not</hi> done. This is evident from the Bill which ſhall be brought in and found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Delinquent, and is already declar'd by our Bleſſed Lord, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. where every Article of the Inditement is Negative, <hi>You did not feed me, you did not cloath me, you did not viſit me,</hi> and the reſt. But here is not alledg'd ſo much as the breach of a Commandment; then Irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Luxury, Detraction and Extortion are ſmaller Crimes, which will bear no Action. But ſince leſſer Articles cannot ſuperſede the greater, it follows, Theſe are upon another Rule, unleſs ſuch groſs offenders ſhall be ranged with Infidels, <hi>who are already judg'd,</hi> and carry their Sentence in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31122:4"/>their Faces, <hi>jam judicati ſunt.</hi> But for the reſt of Chriſtians, who think themſelves innocent becauſe they abſtain from theſe blacker Crimes, it is neceſſary another Inditement ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd, ſetting forth the Omiſſion of good Works, and convicting them of miſpending their Time, which, as appears from our Saviours words, is alone ſufficient to plunge them into everlaſting Flames, <hi>Quia non feciſtis.</hi> Therefore, <hi>becauſe you did not,</hi> for no other reaſon, <hi>go you curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after all this, amidſt ſo much knowledge in a Point which concerns us ſo highly, and which we firmly believe, is it not a Subject rather of Tears than of Expoſtulation and Diſcourſe, that nothing is ſo little conſider'd by Man, as the true value of Time? I know the Divine, the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, the Lawyer, the Trades-man, and even the Libertine unanimouſly agree that Time is the moſt pretious thing in the World, but all of them upon different <hi>Motives.</hi> The Philoſopher prizes it in order to Science, the Lawyer manages it to improve his Fortune, the Trades-man to procure a Subſiſtence, the Libertine to indulge his Appetites, but the Divine teaches it to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly valuable, as leading to an happy Eternity. To value Time upon the account of Speculation, is meerly Heatheniſh; to value it for a Temporal
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31122:5"/>advantage, is meerly Human; <hi>haec Gentes requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt;</hi> to value it for the abuſe of it, is diabolical; but to value it for the true end, is the eſtimate of a Chriſtian. Wherefore, all the manegery of Time, or rather the applying of it otherwiſe than to the true end, for which it was given, and to which it naturally tends <hi>i. e.</hi> to Eternity, is an unjuſt alienation, becauſe it turns the Means into the end, and fruſtrates the Deſign of God and Nature.</p>
               <p>It is not my buſineſs to ſubtilize upon the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Time,</hi> or Metaphyſically enquire what it is, whether <hi>the revolution of the Heavens,</hi> or <hi>the meaſure of the motion and reſt of Bodies,</hi> or <hi>a particle of Eternity which we now uſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic. I.</hi> 1. <hi>de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. Rhet.</hi>
                  </note> as the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor calls it? Let us leave this diſquiſition to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. There is a certain <hi>Definition</hi> which every Chriſtian carries in his Breaſt, that it is a Term aſſign'd us by Providence, to work out our Salvation in it. This <hi>Term</hi> is diverſify'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſeveral Men it affects; and what is many Years to one, is but a few Months, or Days, or Hours to another. Yet this ſhorter Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, is a Mans whole Time, his whole Courſe; as the Moon and other Planets compleat their Revolution and fulfil their Motion, as well as the Sun and Superior Heavens, which are much longer in performing theirs. Wherefore, it is a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31122:5"/>aſtrange Folly, and little leſs than Impiety, which is ſo common in every bodies mouth, that ſuch an one came to an untimely end, or was cut off in the Flower or middle of his Age, when that very Perſon ſo lamented as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripe for the Sythe, had liv'd out his <hi>whole time</hi> as well as <hi>Mathuſalem;</hi> and ſo has the Infant who is taken in the Womb, or having <hi>but one day upon the Earth,</hi> as much as <hi>the Child of an hundred years,</hi> as the Scripture moſt properly ſtiles thoſe who end their days in ſuch Puerili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as they began them, with as little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration why they came into the World, what they are to do in it, what Account will be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded after it; Their Divertiſements and what they call Pleaſures, being as ſilly, and wanting nothing of the Child, but <hi>Innocence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if it be agreed on, that <hi>Time is pretious,</hi> what Frenzy has ſeiz'd Mankind, and makes them ſo laviſh of what they eſteem ſo dear? What Spirit makes us ſo fond and careful of Temporal advantages, ſo greedy of what is not our own, and ſo negligent of the thing which only belongs to us?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnes ſi qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem res aliena a nobus eſt, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus autem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum eſt.</hi> Bern. l. Medit. c. 6. Senec.</note> For as <hi>Seneca</hi> and St. <hi>Bernard</hi> admirably obſerve, all other things are Foreign, nothing is properly ours, but Time: Or ſuppoſing other things to be never ſo much our own, yet the value of Time ought in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31122:6"/>reaſon to be greater than the eſtimation of what we only owe to Time; and who ſquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it away, tho he pretend to Prudence and Conduct in other matters, can deſerve that ſtile no better, than one who receives his Rents with great exactneſs and circumſpection, but keeps no account how he lays them out; or, another who buſies himſelf about what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to him, or is exact in trivial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but neglects the main; like that unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Prince, who valu'd himſelf more upon the touch of the Lute, than the Art of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>All other things are Foreign to us, <hi>aliena à nobis ſunt;</hi> they are beneath us; we now and then deſcend to them out of <hi>neceſſity</hi> or for <hi>diverſion,</hi> but the management of Time is the <hi>buſineſs of Man.</hi> This only is our own, but it will not ſtay with us; it is <hi>ſhort</hi> and <hi>ſwift,</hi> properties which inhaunce the value, and ſhew it was given us only for uſe. Part of it ſteals away from us before we reflect upon it, part others ſteal from us; and of that which we are actually uſing, a great deal runs at waſte. For ſetting aſide the Years of our undiſcerning <hi>Childhood,</hi> and inconſiderate <hi>Youth,</hi> and unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Old Age,</hi> only the middle part of our Lives, which hardly make up a fourth, we think worth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31122:6"/>improving; and how few arrive to this term? Not the fourth part of Mankind; and of thoſe that do, not the Hundreth part, I am afraid, ever think whereabouts they are, but trifle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the preſent, which is in their power, to build their hopes upon a future, in which it is at leaſt <hi>probable</hi> they ſhall have no ſhare, and in which <hi>for certain,</hi> they will be more unfit for labor. But of this riper and more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted part of our Lives, how much is taken up in neceſſary attendance on our <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> how much conſum'd in <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſts,</hi> how much in <hi>refreſhing the Spirits</hi> and <hi>unbending the Mind?</hi> And of the remainder, which amounts not to above a fifteenth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, how much is waſted in Diſquiſition and Error, and miſtaking our buſineſs, in idle expectation, fond hopes and unactive fears? And after all this ſubduction, have we time to ſpend in uſeleſs Diſcourſes, imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent News, tedious Viſits or unprofitable Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? But it ſeems we have ſo much plenty ſtill, that every Senſe and Appetite puts in for a ſhare, and wantons away the ſelect and more pretious hours. We have time for Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Cheating and Circumventing, Slander and Detraction, Luxury and Murder, and, as if <hi>the wickedneſs of the day were not ſufficient
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31122:7"/>for it,</hi> we take in great part of the Night. We ſuffer every one, who has a mind to loſe his own time, to make bold with ours; and when all other Injuries and uſurpation of our Goods is preſently inform'd againſt, and proſecuted as far as the Crime will bear, even to death, for a Garment or a ſmall Sum of Mony; there is no Man brings an Action againſt the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor that <hi>robs us of ſo much time</hi> in formal Viſits or unprofitable Diſcourſe, nay, we are not ſenſible he has done us any wrong; but ſoon after we grow weary of the <hi>reſt,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to do the ſame injury to others, inviting them to ſpend an hour in this or that diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement. <hi>To ſpend an hour?</hi> (cries St. <hi>Bernard,) Do you know what you ſay! To ſpend an hour, which the mercy of your Creator has indulg'd you to do Penance, to obtain Pardon, to acquire Grace and purchaſe Glory?</hi> O donec pertranſeat tempus! <hi>To paſs the time away in which you ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the Divine Juſtice, to haſten towards an Angelical Purity, to bewail your paſt offences;</hi> the Evangelical Treaſure which you ought to buy with the expence of all you have. To ſpend the time! O abſurdity of ſpeech! O ſtupidity of mind! To quicken the ſpeed of Time, which is ever upon the wing, and cannot be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſtay with us. If we manage our Time
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31122:7"/>to ſo much advantage, what pity it is we are confin'd to ſo ſmall a compaſs, and our lives crowded into ſo narrow a ſpace! Great pity indeed, that Men, who Husband a little ſo well, have not a larger Fortune to improve! a ſad thing, that from amidſt theſe laudable Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes one muſt be ſnatch'd away on a ſuddain, as if our Induſtry and Application had not me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited a longer term!</p>
               <p>But, Chriſtians, let us once in our lives be ſerious, and conſider in cold Blood what we are doing, whiles ſo great a Treaſure ſlips between our fingers! Let us once in our lives tell true, and ingenuouſly confeſs what we are driving at, what we hope to gain by ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious and irrecoverable an Expence? I dare not tell you St. <hi>Bernards</hi> opinion of your Proceedings, That all the time you have not God before your eyes, is to be reckon'd as loſt:
<note place="margin">Bern. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clam.</note> 
                  <hi>Omne tempus in quo de Deo non cogitas, hoc te computes perdidiſſe.</hi> But this I am bold to affirm, that all Time not ſpent in order to Eternity, is miſ-ſpent; if employed only upon things <hi>indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> it is to be accounted for, if upon things <hi>criminal,</hi> it is to be ſatisfy'd for, if it be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd; and even thoſe Actions which paſs for the moſt <hi>innocent,</hi> when not directed to the right end, become defective, and in ſome meaſure
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31122:8"/>criminal; nay, even things neceſſary, when they exceed the limits of neceſſity, are put to the account of miſ-ſpending. I need not ſpeak of Time ſpent in thoſe things, which even the corruption of this Age, with all its gloſſes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Varniſh over, which appear in their own Colours, do what we can, and condemn us while they are acting. I need not ſpeak of Time ſpent in ſantring up and down, hearing or relating News, Dancing, Gaming, which have not any other end than a ſhort refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Spirits, beyond which, they are amuſements, which we tolerate in Children, and nothing but want of Reaſon can excuſe; For aſſure your ſelves, want of Reflection in a riper Age will not do it; for how can Not-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting excuſe us, when Ignorance it ſelf ſhall be reputed a Crime, and <hi>he that do's not know, ſhall not be known?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now go and tell me your State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not allow you to ſpend your Time better; if this be ſo, that State of yours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves very ill of you; it is unlawful in it ſelf, and therefore to be abandon'd: And methinks, no one ſhould be unwilling to quit that miſerable Servitude where he has not lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be good. But if the State be good, it is ſanctify'd by vertuous Practices; and if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31122:8"/>you ſuperſede that Sanctification, you render that Criminal, which of it ſelf is good and laudable. But the goodneſs of moſt States de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the execution of them.</p>
               <p>It was a common Saying among the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, That every Man is the Artificer of his own Fortune; I am ſure, every one is the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer of his own Happineſs, who by co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating with the Grace and Time which is given him, may improve the moſt ordinary Actions into vertuous and meritorious, or by neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this caſie improvement, render himſelf accountable for the moſt indifferent things.</p>
               <p>That Direction of the Apoſtle, <hi>Whether you eat or drink, or whatſoever you do, do all to the Glory of God,</hi> is a Precept (for ſo the Fathers ſtile it,) of a vaſt extent, and reaches not only the more <hi>remarkable,</hi> but alſo takes in the <hi>minuteſt Actions,</hi> and every moment of our Lives. In the Eyes of God a thouſand Years are but a moment, and in the Service of God a moment may be worth a thouſand Years; it may redeem an Age, it may purchaſe an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Unhappy Man! who neglects a moment, which may render him ſo for ever! <hi>à momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Aeternitas;</hi> Eternity depends upon a moment, becauſe Eternity is the end of Time, which is nothing but a Flux of moments; and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31122:9"/>which will certainly happen in one, may happen in any one.</p>
               <p>And now certainly, I have ſaid enough of the due value of Time, which muſt be preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, as well to the appretiation and eſteem of the thing, as to the redeeming of it. If you are ſatisfy'd in the value of it, you cannot but be griev'd to the very heart, that you have part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it ſo eaſily, paſs'd it over ſo ſlightly, and ſpent it ſo idly and irreligiouſly, and by conſequence, will be very glad to hear how you may redeem it, which is the Subject of my <hi>Second Part.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Redeem the Time.</head>
               <p>The higheſt point of Wiſdom that Man can arrive to by Philoſophy, is to make uſe of his Time when it is in his hands; but to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it when it is gone, to retrieve it when it is loſt; to rectifie the Errors and Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of it when it is no more, is one of thoſe Arcanums of Religion, which are hid from the Wiſe and reveal'd to Babes. It was the Saying of <hi>Pittacus,</hi> celebrated ſo much by Antiquity, and which entitled him to a place among the wiſeſt of Men, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Learn to value your Time,</hi> but <hi>to redeem it</hi> was a Leſſon
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31122:9"/>that great Maſter never learn'd himſelf, and became only an Apoſtle of the Church to teach. But who is able to pay ſo great a Ranſom? And what Exchange can one make for his Time, more than for his own Soul? The price is eaſie and obvious, and in every Mans power, <hi>Cautè ambulate,</hi> only <hi>walk warily,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>circumſpectly</hi> and <hi>watchfully;</hi> do now what before you ought to have done, and a guard upon your Actions for the future, ſhall repair the damages caus'd by your former negligence. But <hi>walking warily,</hi> implies not only a Ceſſation from Evil, but alſo a Repentance of it; To redeem the Time there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſaith St. <hi>Anſelm,</hi> is to redeem the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Miſ-ſpent Life, with Tears and peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Works, <hi>Eſt anteactae vitae peccata, flendo, &amp; poenitendo redimere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Sorrow then is a Tear, which cannot recover the ſmalleſt Temporal loſs, ſo valuable in order to Eternity; and do our Hearts remain ſtill without ſenſe, and our Eyes without moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture? Will amendment for the future croſs the Book? Will an <hi>humble acknowledgment</hi> of the Debt compound with our Adverſary in the way? Will a <hi>preſent diligence,</hi> in performing what is otherwiſe our Duty, attone for ſo much negligence in managing the <hi>Talent</hi> depoſited in our hands? And is the Price thought too dear
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31122:10"/>with us? Or do we ſtand with our Hands in our Pockets, demurring upon the Bargain? Do's not <hi>Reaſon</hi> as well as <hi>Religion</hi> prompt us to lay hold of it immediately? And ſince the Mercy of our God is ſo liberal, to take him at his word, (as I may ſay,) and enter the Vineyard this very moment, tho at the 9th, tho at the 11th hour, when the ſhort remainder of the time may make up the loſs of all the reſt! Oh! the unſpeakable comforts of this Promiſe! Oh! the incredible ſtupidity of Man! which ſtands unmov'd at ſuch large Invitations, ſuch a general Amneſty, ſuch unexpected Promiſes, as tranſcend not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a reaſonable Hope, but even the boldeſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Morning comes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 21.12.</note> (ſays the Prophet,) <hi>and alſo the Night;</hi> tho your Day be far ſpent, there is ſtill Time enough to enquire after the means of your Salvation; <hi>Si quaeritis, quaerite, If you ſeek, ſeek in earneſt, return and come:</hi> And that we ſhould not doubt of a merciful Reception, he gives us this aſſurance by another Prophet, <hi>That he will forgive our Iniquity, and that he will remember our ſin no more.</hi> Jer. 31.34.</p>
               <p>Surely, there is ſome unknown Pleaſure and invincible Faſcination in Idleneſs, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be unti'd by ſuch powerful Countercharms as theſe. Cuſtom, (which is but ſtanding Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,)
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31122:10"/>has prepoſſeſs'd our Minds, ſtupifi'd and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſed in Fleſh and Blood; that <hi>to do nothing</hi> is <hi>eaſie,</hi> when indeed it is the greateſt <hi>pain</hi> the reaſonable Creature can endure; arguing either a childiſh <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> that we cannot act, or a ſhameful <hi>Ignorance,</hi> that we know not what to do. And I believe the Man of Reaſon will grant me, that Ignorance, as it is a puniſhment upon us for doing what we ought not, ſo is it the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt torment to a Soul, which is perpetually thirſting after Knowledge: And as for the more unthinking and groſſer part of Mankind, they cannot deny, but all Pain comes from Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Our own Notions therefore bear teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt us; and if what we call a gentile life, ſpeaks either our <hi>Weakneſs</hi> or <hi>Ignorance,</hi> the gentile Liver is the moſt unhappy Creature in the World: For Happineſs is ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in either of <hi>theſe,</hi> that both are eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtructive to it; and whoſoever hopes to compaſs this end by contrary means, will find himſelf at laſt in the other Extremity. To be plain, whoſoever promiſes Happineſs to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf without much labor, ſets it at too high a price, at which no wiſe Man would buy it, if it be not to be purchas'd but by living idly; for at this rate, one muſt be Miſerable to become Happy.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:31122:11"/>
               <p>But how unnatural a thing is it for that Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be idle,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambr. Praef. in Luc. Baſil. ap. Mel.</hi> 89.</note> who alone of all Creatures ſtands condemn'd to labor? as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerves: Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which conſideration St. <hi>Baſil</hi> doubts not to brand this Vice of ſo great reputation in the World, with the infamous Character of <hi>a ſin againſt Nature;</hi> becauſe there is nothing in the whole Frame of Nature idle or unactive. Our Bleſſed Saviour teſtifies of the Godhead it ſelf, <hi>My Father</hi> (ſaith he,)
<note place="margin">John 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtill works, and I work; Pater meus uſque modo operatur.</hi> All the Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches of Angels (as one aſſures us, who had been in the third Heaven,) <hi>are Adminiſtring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits:</hi> The Prophet declares, they have no reſt day nor night; but inceſſantly pour forth their harmonious Acclamation, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God of Sabbath:</hi> And what I ſhould have mention'd before, The ſacred Humanity of Chriſt <hi>came not to be ſerv'd, but to ſerve; Non venit ut Miniſtraretur, ſed ut Miniſtraret.</hi> The Celeſtial Orbs have never had any reſpite from their perpetual motion; all things below are in a continual Tide, a regular Succeſſion of Cauſes and Effects; <hi>Every Creature groans, and brings forth even till now,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle: And if <hi>the inviſible things of God are underſtood by thoſe things which are made,</hi> The Operations of Nature are ſo many Emblems of the Diligence he requires
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31122:11"/>at our hands towards the working out our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; God having made them not only for our <hi>uſe,</hi> but alſo for our <hi>inſtruction.</hi> In fine, the whole World is a large Volum, as St.
<note place="margin">S. <hi>Athanaſ. in Vit.</hi> S. <hi>Ant.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> calls it, where we may read our Duty, and meet with it in every line. Nay, if Man would but take the meaſure of his <hi>Moral Actions</hi> from the obſervation of his <hi>Natural,</hi> the continual working of the Heart, circulation of the Blood, reſpiration of the Lungs, pulſe of the Arteries and activity of the Fancy, will teach him Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity in the exerciſe of thoſe nobler Faculties, whoſe Actions depend upon the liberty of his Will; how conſtant and regular his Motion ought to be in the Service of God; And that his Soul is as much <hi>dead,</hi> when it is idle, and ſurceaſes from doing well, as the Body will be, when all theſe Vital Operations are at an end.</p>
               <p>I know not any one, who would not eſteem it a horrible Execration, to wiſh he had neither Hands nor Feet; yet, ſuch is our miſery, that while we make no more uſe of them in order to our own good, or that of our Neighbor, than if they were quite diſabled; even in that reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect we count our ſelves happy: For take away from the Lady, the Gentleman, the Courtier, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the power and convenience of doing nothing, and <hi>being not in the labors of Men,</hi> the ſubtileſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31122:12"/>Logician can ſcarce explain in what formality, their Happineſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> the advantage of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition conſiſts? Their <hi>priviledge</hi> ſeems to lie in an exemption from the general Malediction inflicted upon the reſt of Mankind; <hi>In the ſweat of their brows they ſhall eat their Bread:</hi> But then they muſt draw their Pedegree from ſome other Line than that of <hi>Adam;</hi> for no more is any Child of his free of this Obligation, than he is from the cauſe of it; and if we Inherit the one, we muſt neceſſarily be partakers of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For as Holy <hi>Job</hi> expounds this Sentence, <hi>Man is born to labor;</hi> Labor being not only a neceſſary means to preſerve his life, but one of the ends why it was given him. And our Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour revives and inforces this Doctrin, in the Parable of the Maſter entruſting his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with ſo many Talents, with a <hi>Negotiamini, Manage and improve them;</hi> and this not for a ſpirt, when the fit takes you, but <hi>donec veniam,</hi> without intermiſſion till he calls <hi>them</hi> in, and <hi>you</hi> to give an account of your Stewardſhip; by which <hi>Servants,</hi> every body underſtands the whole Maſs of Human Nature, without except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any State or Condition; and by the <hi>Talents,</hi> a neceſſity of working, according to the Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties this great Maſter has diſpenſed to every particular.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:31122:12"/>
               <p>Now if a Man who had well conſider'd the weight and ſtrictneſs of this Obligation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing the Follies of Mankind, and their vain amuſements, ſhould look out into the World, he would tell me, I make a Diſcourſe in the Air, and to the Walls; for every one is active in his reſpective Station, and employ'd in his Duty, when he ſhould ſee their earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at ſuch a diſtance, as not to diſcern the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are ſo intent upon: How People haſt along the Streets, and preſs one another like Waves, which are broken and ſever'd with a contrary Tide: When he ſhould behold ſome warmly diſputing at a Table, others walking muſing and ſolitary, ſome Reading, others diſcourſing with abundance of Gravity, others ſitting in crowds, in recollection and ſilence; he would certainly bid me hold my peace, and not diſturb theſe ſerious Men, with adviſing them to begin, what they are already doing. But if I ſhould lead him nearer to them, within ken of their Actions, and hearing of their Diſcourſe, when he ſhould diſcover their <hi>Lives</hi> and their <hi>Talk</hi> to be all of a piece, <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt; When he ſhould ſee theſe People running to a Shew or to a Riot, to circumvent their Neighbor, or to oppreſs the Innocent; or cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing about the Streets, meerly to ſhew their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31122:13"/>Equipage or themſelves: When he ſhould find thoſe ſilent and recollected People at the <hi>Theater,</hi> whom he thought at a Sermon; That Lady at her Glaſs, and in a profound contemplation of her ſelf, whom he thought at her <hi>Oratory;</hi> that Gallant reading a <hi>Romance</hi> or a Novel, which he miſtook for a <hi>Prayer-Book:</hi> When he ſhould hear others talking profanely in the very Church, blaſpheming the Divinity they pretend to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, pretending to Reaſon, and yet practiſing Debauchery. In fine, moſt Men acting and talking after ſuch a manner, that what is count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt innocent Diſcourſe, is <hi>Murther,</hi> I mean, cenſuring their Neighbors Actions, and taking their Lives in pieces, as if they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecting an Anatomy, to diſcover the root of a Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p>In a word, When he ſhould be ſatisfy'd, that the plurality of Men is buſied in <hi>unlawful,</hi> or <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> or <hi>trivial</hi> things, and almoſt <hi>all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their buſineſs,</hi> he would cry out, They want a Phyſician more than a Divine; and I ſpend my Time as unprofitably as the reſt, with Preaching to Men in a Lunacy.</p>
               <p>But if he ſhould be commanded with the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 8.8.</note> 
                  <hi>to pierce the Wall,</hi> and view the <hi>Abominations</hi> that are done within, and <hi>all the Idols of the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, with the ſeveral
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31122:13"/>ſorts of Adorations which are paid to them; as the avaricious Man ſacrificing his Soul to a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Gain, the voluptuous Man to his ſenſual Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, the Vindictive to a brutal Revenge, the Ambitious to the ſhadow of Honor, the Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the moſt infamous of Paſſion, the Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer burning Incenſe to his Prince, and the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite to his God; he muſt needs conclude that true, what the Jews ſaid in their Conventicle of Vice, <hi>The Lord hath forſaken the Earth,</hi> and the Fear of him is wholly extinguiſh'd.</p>
               <p>But if amidſt this Mans aſtoniſhment, one ſhould bid him have a care what he ſays, for theſe are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Men who make a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their Actions, People of Credit and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, who would not do an ill thing for the World, who believe they ſhall account ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for every <hi>idle word,</hi> and every <hi>moment</hi> ſpent unprofitably. In ſhort, That they are <hi>redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Time,</hi> and are heartily ſorry for all their ſins, tho they appear to be actually inflaming the reckoning; that they are executing their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and putting their morning Reſolutions in practice, tho they ſeem to be at the Gaming-houſe, the Theater or Tavern; would not he turn upon me as one of the number of mad Men, or an impudent Cheat, endeavoring to impoſe upon his Senſes, and obtrude the groſeſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31122:14"/>
                  <hi>impoſſibilities,</hi> and moſt palpable <hi>contradictions</hi> upon his certain Knowledge and Reaſon?</p>
               <p>Yet whether this be not the preſent State of this Nation, I mean, the caſe of moſt People, <hi>Judicate domus</hi> Iſrael, your Judgment, O Houſe of <hi>Iſrael!</hi> If God ſhould once again ſend the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> to ſearch every Street, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire out a juſt and ſober Man, <hi>any one who ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Truth,</hi> I am perſuaded, he would bring in the ſame Evidence he did before;
<note place="margin">Jerem 5.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt ſtricken them, but they have not griev'd; Thou haſt conſumed them, but they have refus'd to hear cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; They have made their faces harder than a Rock, they have refus'd to return.</hi> The more Time thou giveſt them to repent, the more Time thou alloweſt them to ſin; they are ſo far from <hi>redeeming</hi> what is paſt, that there is like to be no end of the Score.</p>
               <p>But <hi>perhaps they are poor and fooliſh, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the ways of our Lord, and the Judgments and Law of their God;</hi> Vadam ergo ad Optimates, <hi>I will go therefore to the great,</hi> the moſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſcerning Men, the advantage of whoſe <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Education</hi> has rais'd them above the Level, and purg'd their Heads from that Groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Phlegm which ſtupifies the reſt; for <hi>they</hi> cannot but <hi>know the way of the Lord, and the judgment of their God:</hi> Sed hi ſimul confrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31122:14"/>jugum, ruperunt vincula; <hi>But theſe have altogether broken the Yoke, and burſt the Bonds.</hi> At their looking out into the World, their firſt buſineſs is to forget the Religious Education of their tender Age, and to efface the inſtructions of their Parents and Preceptors, by doing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing they were forbid. The firſt Tincture they receive from the World, is <hi>Vanity,</hi> which as <hi>Job</hi> obſerves, ſoon ripens into Pride, <hi>[Vir vanus in ſuperbiam erigitur,]</hi> and then they <hi>think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves born as free and lawleſs as a wild Aſs-colt in the Deſert.</hi> Becauſe they have no neceſſity of ſweating for their Living, they think themſelves <hi>Maſters of their Time;</hi> becauſe Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence has provided ſo largely for them, as to exempt them from the <hi>Drudgery</hi> of the World, and ſet them apart for <hi>nobler Actions;</hi> they think their <hi>Buſineſs</hi> lies only where their <hi>Pleaſures</hi> do. What a frightful Idea have theſe Men of Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, when their own Judgment places them in the State of corrupted and abandon'd Nature, endow'd only with a <hi>liberty to Sin,</hi> or rather in the State of <hi>Damnation,</hi> a <hi>Non-neceſſity</hi> of doing well?</p>
               <p>But, my Noble Auditory, how can you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſo mean or cruel a thought of God, as to fancy he has made a Law from which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empts that ſort of Mankind, which is the <hi>moſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31122:15"/>able</hi> and <hi>beſt qualified</hi> to perform it? Or that he has ſingled out the <hi>beſt part</hi> of his Creation, Men and Women of moſt ſenſe and reaſon, as the fatteſt Victims for Sacrifice, to ſpend their Time in ſilence and idleneſs, and not to be in the labors of Men, aſſigning them no Province, no Soil to cultivate, that they might have no means toward their Reprobation? If this be the end of your Creation, O ye Men of Greatneſs, of Riches and Honors! I cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with Tears, that you ſo well correſpond with it. But if the <hi>advantage</hi> of your conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts in a <hi>capacity</hi> of ſerving God and your Neighbor in a more excellent manner, as well through the great <hi>leiſure</hi> you enjoy, as the <hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>power</hi> you have to do it with, your Time is ſo much more <hi>valuable,</hi> as it may be more <hi>beneficial;</hi> it is more eaſily <hi>redeemed,</hi> by the many <hi>Expedients</hi> which are before you, and the <hi>abuſe</hi> of it ſo much more enormous and puniſhable; upon which that Comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Holy Ghoſt is grounded, <hi>Potentes potenter tormenta patientur, The great ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer great Torments;</hi> and again, <hi>Quantum ſeſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altavit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As much as he has exalted himſelf; and bin in delights, give him ſo much Torment and Grief.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:31122:15"/>
               <p>My Time will not allow me to inſtance in every particular advantage of your State; but give me leave to conclude this Diſcourſe with one which comprehends the reſt, and ſeems to be the property of the Nobles and Gentry, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion. If this be a Duty incumbent upon all Men, ſo that no State, no Circumſtance or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition can preſcribe againſt it, <hi>in capite Libri ſcriptum eſt de vobis,</hi> you are the firſt in the Role, as being Emancipated from thoſe ties and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances, in which the laboring, that is, the far greater part of the World is involv'd. If the Laborer, who moils all day to procure a ſmall refreſhment for his craving Appetite, or to ſupport a Family, be not excus'd upon that account, from conſecrating his Actions in the Morning by Prayer, and giving an account of them in an Evening Recollection; ſhall you be paſs'd by as <hi>Extralineary,</hi> who may perform that almoſt every hour of the day, which the reſt cannot but at ſet intervals, and borrowing Time from their Reſt? If that complaint, which is ſo common in every bodies mouth, <hi>That they have not Time to ſay their Prayers,</hi> be injurious to God, and an implicite accuſation of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, as if it had not furniſh'd us means to perform the Duty it enjoyns? What name ſhall we find for thoſe falſe pretexts and fond excuſes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31122:16"/>which you make, for whom that Precept ſeems to be more particularly calculated, <hi>ſine inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſione orate, pray without ceaſing?</hi> If a ſick Man complain of want of health, or a poor Man of want of Neceſſaries, he becomes an object of Compaſſion, and it would be the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Barbarity to revile him for what is not in his power to avoid. But if a Man in perfect Health ſhould complain of a Diſtemper, or one ſitting at a good Table, ſhould cry he is almoſt famiſh'd, <hi>riſum teneatis amici?</hi> Nobody would refrain from laughter: and yet it is incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly more abſurd for any one to complain he has not Time to pray, which he ought to be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing while he is complaining. But for thoſe who have nothing elſe to do, or at the moſt, only incident and caſual avocations, it is a ſubject of Tears, and a folly to which one would think Men of good ſenſe, of all people in the World ſhould be the leaſt ſubject. You have not time to Pray; but you have time to be Drunk; You have not time to Pray; but you have time to ſpend in idle diſcourſe, in ſcandalous and uncharitable Reflections, <hi>in chambering and wantonneſs.</hi> You have not time to Pray, but how many hours do you waſt in <hi>Gaming,</hi> when the loſs of your Mony, is the leaſt expence; and what you gain, cannot redeem, is not the price of a moment of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31122:16"/>the Time you loſe? O Heavens! how glad will ye be one day of half an hour, out of ſo many thouſands which dance over your heads unregarded! what would not a Damn'd ſoul give for thoſe ſcraps of Time, which you caſt away as ſuperfluous?</p>
               <p>But certainly, <hi>the man of buſineſs</hi> has not Time to be devout: yet he has Time, but it ſeems not to that end; or if to that end, yet Affairs of a greater importance intervene and challenge it to themſelves. If it be ſo, the Man of buſineſs is, by neceſſity, the moſt Irreligious perſon in the world: For if you prefer any thing to your Prayers, it is an evident ſign you judge it of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter importance, which is a <hi>Spiritual Idolatry,</hi> poſtponing the Creator to the Creature. But if you acknowledg thoſe things you prefer to your Prayers, to be of an <hi>Inferior order,</hi> you are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unjuſt. No wonder then if at thoſe few bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken moments, and ends of Time, which are the Refuſe of your pleaſure, or what you miſcal, your buſineſs, when you vouchſafe to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Divine Majeſty with defil'd Hands, and a Mind painted all over with the imagery of of Creatures, and a Heart totally immerſed in ſenſual, if not criminal, affections; no wonder I ſay, if your Prayers are not heard, which drop from you with as ill a Grace, as Alms from the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31122:17"/>Miſer, which are huddled over with as much precipitation, as if you were making an eſcape from God Almighty, which are accompanied with ſo many indignities, that you bid fair with <hi>Jacob</hi> for a <hi>Curſe</hi> rather than a Bleſſing, and fall upon your Knees, not to obtain <hi>pardon,</hi> but to receive <hi>ſentence,</hi> or rather to increaſe your <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſuch as the Royal Prophet wiſhes the counterfeit Repentant, <hi>Oratio ejus fiat in pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum;</hi> your very Prayer becomes an additional ſin.</p>
               <p>I know ſome will be apt to think, ſurely this Man miſtakes his Auditory, and fancies himſelf preaching in a Cloyſter, or reading Aſcetick Lectures to People wholly eſtrang'd and ſecluded from the World. But they may ſpare that thought: I know the place I fill, I know and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere my Auguſt and noble Audience; I am ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I am ſpeaking, as in the moſt Awful, ſo to the moſt diſcerning, ingenious, letter'd, and judicious Aſſembly of the World. I ſpeak to a Court, to Men of Buſineſs, and whoſe Time is much taken up with weighty imployments: I ſpeak to the Flower of both Sexes; I ſpeak to Ladies, Souldiers, Philoſophers and Divines; but that is not all, I ſpeak to <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and if any appear not in that Quality, I ſpeak not to them: But all who own that Character, muſt at
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31122:17"/>the ſame time render to my Doctrin. I do not perſwade you to <hi>relinquiſh,</hi> but to <hi>ſanctify</hi> your ſtate; and certainly <hi>Piety, which is profitable to all things,</hi> is more than ordinarily <hi>neceſſary</hi> to them, who are ſurrounded with more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary dangers, which renders Prayer more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in a Court than in a Convent; Becauſe, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerves, Temptations there, are more ſerpentine and wily, more rife and allur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Pavement more ſlippery where one ſtands, the Bruiſe greater when one falls, and the Riſe more difficult when one is down. The ſame I affirm reſpectivly of every ſtate which admits of many diſtractions, and very much engages and takes up the mind; as thoſe Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers need the frequenter Antidotes which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the oftneſt, and lye heavieſt at the heart; which renders this Verity clear and beyond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, That a <hi>Monk</hi> in his Cell is not half ſo criminal in omitting the ſolemn obligations of his Order, as a Courtier who diſpenſes with himſelf in the conſtant obſervance of Piety, how plauſible and ſpecious ſoever his pretences may be. Tell me not of the contrary Judgment of the World, <hi>which is all plac'd in iniquity;</hi> no Man chuſes his enemy to be his Judg. We are not to bend our Rule to the Practice or opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Men, but we reduce them to the Rule,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31122:18"/>and by <hi>that</hi> pronounce of their Rectitude or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquity; <hi>ad Legem magis et Prophetas:</hi> We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide not matters of <hi>Right</hi> by matters of <hi>Fact,</hi> but the contrary; we judg of the Lawfulneſs of the Action by comparing it with the Law.</p>
               <p>To conclude. The Time is <hi>pretious;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are commanded to be watchful how every moment of it goes away, <hi>vigilate ita<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omni tempore: It is ſhort;</hi> and what follows, ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>but that thoſe who uſe this world, be as if they us'd it not?</hi> that is, even they who have moſt to do in the World, are to be ſo intent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the managing their Time, that the World ſhould rather ſteal from them, than their Time. It is <hi>the only thing we can call our own,</hi> therefore let us preſerve it; <hi>Fili, conſerva tempus:</hi> but <hi>it is ſwift,</hi> therefore let us work while we have it, <hi>dum habemus operemur;</hi> but <hi>it is evil,</hi> therefore let us ſanctify it, <hi>operemur bonum;</hi> but much of it is <hi>already waſted,</hi> therefore let us redeem it, before our Glaſs be out:
<note place="margin">Revel. 10.</note> for <hi>he that has ſworn by him who lives for ever, that Time ſhall be no more,</hi> hath warn'd us, <hi>that fatal Period is very neer: Tempus prope eſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 1.</note> This life is the time of Labor, and the ſervice of God the chief buſineſs of Man, from which no one is exempted, and they <hi>the leaſt,</hi> as I have ſhewn, who think they have the beſt Plea. It is in the power but of a few to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31122:18"/>conſecrate themſelves entirly to the ſervice of God, but to admit Temporal affairs in their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and range them in a ſecondary place, is the Duty of every one. It is impoſſible to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar our ſelves all Recreations and Paſtimes, but very poſſible, and even neceſſary, to chuſe thoſe which are <hi>innocent:</hi> The Heathen Philoſopher will not allow you others than ſuch as are <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable</hi> and <hi>beneficial:</hi> No one for his recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to deſcend from good Actions to bad: no one to ſpend his Time has leave to miſpend it. Let us ſum up all that has been ſaid, in the wiſe Mans advice directed to every ſtate and condition, <hi>Whatſoever thy hand findeth to do,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>do it with thy might,</hi> (Inſtanter, <hi>with diligence and ſpeed</hi>) <hi>for their is no work nor device, nor knowledg, nor wiſdom in the Grave, whither thou art haſtning:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quo tu prope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras.</hi> Dulg.</note> And to which I beſeech God of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to prepare Us all by a ſpeedy Repentance for having <hi>miſpent</hi> ſo much of our time, and an earneſt endeavour to <hi>Redeem</hi> it, <hi>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
